Okay folks, 46th day of the עומר, Omer, we're almost there. Okay.
Today's דף Daf is דף ג. Daf Gimmel.
נדה, Niddah, we start at the very top, very first word. We
had just been looking at the case in the משנה Mishnah of
a woman who finds that she's a נדה. Niddah. How much back
does she have to be concerned that she might have bled without
realizing it? שמאי Shammai says she can assume it only happened right
now. הלל Hillel says all the way back to the last time
she checked
and it's assumed that she had she
she got her period. Before she gets the period, she's supposed to
feel.
Well, oh, you know what? That is exactly what the גמרא Gemara
is going to say today. Joe, thank you, that is exactly what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say today. So we'll get back
to that. Okay, so שמאי Shammai says you don't have to be
concerned it happened before. הלל Hillel says you have to be concerned
until the last time she checked, and there's a compromise position of
the חכמים Chachamim which we're not up to yet.
So now, based on this, the גמרא's Gemara made a series of
comparisons to other cases where something had a status quo, the status
changed, and when do we assume the problem occurred? Only now that
we find it, all the way back to the last time we
knew it was good? How do we deal with that? Compared it
to a case about a מקוה Mikvah that was missing, a barrel
of wine that the wine turned to vinegar, and so on and
we made distinctions.
And as Joe said actually, and as we pointed out yesterday, you
know, all of that sort of objectifies the woman and does not
focus on the particular subjective reality and also biological reality that goes
on when a woman menstruates, and that actually will come up today
and that is going to be an important discussion today. Okay, but
what we are looking at now is some of the cases we
brought as comparison, and particularly the question about what happens in this
case here with the מקוה Mikvah that was found to be missing
that was found to be not not have the minimum amount of
water, what do we do with everything that was used in the
מקוה Mikvah when we don't know what its status was? And we
said that there's a debate that the חכמים Chachamim say it's definitely
טמא, Tamei, it had a status of being טמא Tamei unless we
know that it's changed, and you don't know that for sure because
the מקוה Mikvah now is found lacking. So it remains definitely טמא.
Tamei. And רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon said it's a ספק. safek. Now
what do you do with a ספק? safek? Well, here we introduce,
and it's interesting, there's big תוספות Tosafot that discuss why we don't
always start talking like this about but we're not going to worry
about that right now. Here we introduce a principle that we learn
from סוטה, Sotah, which is that it matters if it's in a
private domain or in a public domain. So the normal rule is,
when we apply those rules, that if the ספק safek of טומאה
tumah in a private domain, it's טמא, Tamei, in a public domain
it's טהור. tahor. Interesting though, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon does not go
all the way. He says in a private domain it's a ספק,
safek, not טמא, Tamei, and in a public domain it is טהור.
tahor. So we're going to have two questions. What is the debate
of the חכמים Chachamim and רבי שמעון? Rebbe Shimon? The חכמים Chachamim
say it's definitely טמא. Tamei. רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says it's a
doubt. And why does רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon not take the comparison
to סוטה Sotah the full distance? So we pick up with that
on the top of דף ג עמוד א. Daf Gimmel amud aleph.
Let's take a look. ושניהם למדוה אלא מסוטה. Usheineihem lemeduha ela misotah.
Both of them, the Rabbis that say in this מקוה Mikvah case
the vessels that you don't know whether they were dunked properly or
not are definitely טמא, Tamei, and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says it's
a doubt, both of them learned their positions from the model of
סוטה. Sotah. רבנן סברי, Rabbanan savri, כסוטה. kesotah. The Rabbis say just
like סוטה. Sotah. What do you mean just like סוטה? Sotah? מה
סוטה ספק היא ועשוה כודאי. Ma Sotah safek hee ve'asuha kevadei.
The same way a סוטה Sotah is a doubt whether she's committed
adultery, but the תורה Torah says ונטמאה, vehitma'ah, and the Rabbis understand
there that even in the existence of doubt she's treated as ודאי
טמאה, vadai tmeiah, definitely forbidden to her husband until that doubt can
be clarified. And from there they learn the principle of ספק טומאה
ברשות היחיד טמא. safek tumah b'reshut hayachid Tamei. So the same way
by a סוטה Sotah it's a doubt and it's made like it's
definite, הכא נמי ספק ועשוה כודאי. hacha nami safek v'asuha kevadei. Here
too this case about whether the מקוה Mikvah was full or not,
it's a doubt and therefore we treat it as definitely no good.
Of course that's a problem because we only say that by סוטה
Sotah in half the cases, in the private domain. So the גמרא
Gemara says that. Wait a minute. אי מסוטה, Ee misotah, if you're
really using סוטה Sotah as your model, אימא כסוטה. eima kesotah. So
make it like סוטה. Sotah. מה סוטה ברשות הרבים טהור, Ma Sotah
b'reshut harabim tahor, סוטה Sotah we say that when the doubt occurs
in a public domain it's טהור, tahor, she's טהור, tahor, it's טהור.
tahor. הכא נמי ברשות הרבים טהור. Hacha nami b'reshut harabim tahor. Here
too say the same and how come we don't distinguish in the
מקוה Mikvah case and we say whether public or private, it's ודאי
טמא? vadai Tamei? So גמרא Gemara says: הכי השתא? Hachi hashta? One
minute, you can't make the comparison. התם משום סתירה הוא וסתירה ברשות
הרבים ליכא. Hatam mishum stirah hu v'stirah b'reshut harabim leika. There, and
this is an amazing statement and the גמרא's Gemara not going to
stick with it because the גמרא Gemara there added a tremendously logical
statement but it's not the principle we use in ש"ס. shas. It
says, in סוטה Sotah it's really not about a technical question of
private or public domain. What's the reason when a סוטה Sotah is
טמאה? tmeiah? When she goes into private with this man and therefore
there's a concern whether she committed adultery. So the issue is not
a formalistic question of private or public domain. The real issue is
whether... She wasn't private with this man and is there basis to
concern, consider, be concerned that she's committed adultery. So if we're really
using סוטה Sotah as the model and we're being logical about it,
not formalistic about it, we should say: whenever there's a doubt about
טומאה, Tumah, it's טמא. Tamei. The רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim or רשות
היחיד Reshus HaYachid is just a circumstance that's created to create the
doubt. But it really is a question of whenever there's a doubt,
it's טמא, Tamei, if we really were logical about it. Of course,
the problem is that we never say that. We always say by
סוטה Sotah formalistic approach about public versus private. But here, that's what
the גמרא's Gemara going to say, it's going to drop it in
a minute. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: התם, Hasam, let's
read it first: התם משום סתירה היא. Hasam mishum stira hi. There
the reason that she's טמאה, Tmeiah, the importance of the private domain,
is because she's in private, she's secluded. וסתירה ברשות הרבים ליתא, U'stira
b'reshus harabim leisa, and that's not possible in רשות הרבים. Reshus HaRabim.
But it's really not about the formalistic question of private or public.
It's really when there's a basis for doubt. הכא משום חסרו, Hacha
mishum chasro, and here there is a basis for doubt. The מקוה
Mikvah is lacking. מה לי רשות הרבים מה לי רשות היחיד? Mah
li reshus harabim mah li reshus hayachid? What do I care, private
or public domain? That purely formalistic concern has no bearing on the
issue. So what if we really are logical about סוטה, Sotah, the
rule should be a ספק טומאה Safek Tumah is טמא Tamei regardless
of the רשות. Reshus. So the גמרא Gemara says, so okay, that
makes a tremendous amount of sense, but of course it's not what
we say throughout שס. Shas. So the גמרא Gemara does not stick
with it. And the גמרא Gemara says, וכי תימא הכל ספק טומאה
ברשות הרבים טהור? V'chi teima hakol safek tumah b'reshus harabim tahor? But
let
now, let's say you come back and say to me, that's all
very nice and logical but it's not our rule. Our rule is
that a ספק טומאה Safek Tumah in a public domain is טהור
Tahor and we do go, we are formalistic, even when there's a
basis for doubt, if it's the public domain, we say it's טהור.
Tahor. So okay, so now we're back to our question. If סוטה
Sotah is your model, you made a nice argument that from סוטה
Sotah we should say whenever there's a logical basis of doubt we
should say טמא, Tamei, but we don't. We say if it's in
private it's טמא, Tamei, if it's in public it's טהור. Tahor. So
if נידה Niddah is and סוטה Sotah is your model, why in
the מקוה Mikvah case do you say it's always טמא Tamei and
not concern yourself with the רשות? Reshus? Let's read the answer and
then I'll take the questions, thank you. So the answer is, גמרא
Gemara says, כיון דאיכא תרתי לריעותא. Keivan d'ika tartu l'reiusa. No, כיון
דאיכא תרתי לריעותא. Keivan d'ika tartu l'reiusa.
So finally it comes around to also the answer it sort of
knew at the beginning and interestingly here תוספות Tosafos actually says, really
makes the point that גמרא Gemara always knew this answer. But whatever,
it developed its thought and now it came out to the answer
it always knew, which is that the מקוה Mikvah case is special.
There are two things bad. What does it mean two things bad?
Number one, the מקוה Mikvah is lacking. But number two, what really
makes the מקוה Mikvah case special is that the כלים keilim or
the person started out טמא. Tamei. The starting status quo was טמא.
Tamei. So when you have this question of a doubt, yes, there's
a doubt about the מקוה, Mikvah, should we learn it from סוטה
Sotah or not? The answer is no, because here we're trying to
use a doubtful מקוה Mikvah to change a person's status. We know
he's טמא, Tamei, can we say he's טהור? Tahor? And there the
answer is no. That's different from סוטה Sotah and normal cases where
you know I'm טהור Tahor and the question is did I become
טמא? Tamei? So if the question is did I become טמא, Tamei,
you could say well sometimes you'll say yes, sometimes you'll say no,
sometimes we'll be lenient, sometimes whatever, רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim, רשות היחיד.
Reshus HaYachid. But if you know that I'm טמא, Tamei, then it's
like I'm definitely טמא Tamei and unless you definitely can change that,
I remain definitely טמא. Tamei. So in the end, the irony is
that it starts by saying both of them learned it from סוטה,
Sotah, but now we're actually saying, but actually the חכמים Chachamim didn't
learn it from סוטה. Sotah. The סוטה Sotah case is she starts
off טהורה, Tehorah, and like our person starts טהור, Tahor, did you
become טמא? Tamei? Well, that depends: private domain, public domain, what assumptions
we're going to make. But here, that's not relevant. The person started
טמא. Tamei. Did you become טהור Tahor by going into the מקוה?
Mikvah? We're not going to be able to say that you became
טהור Tahor unless we know that for certain. Okay, and that's the
principle of תרתי לריעותא, tarti l'reiusa, same principle we said yesterday, why
we are stricter in the מקוה Mikvah case because we start by
the thing being not good. Michael, you had a question for... Charlie,
question?
This issue of using formal rules rather than what would appear to
be the best evidence, right, and it's almost like
defying
logic. But you're right, we do see that. We see that from
some כשרות Kashrus things.
Right. And it is true, I think we should distinguish between, look,
הלכה Halacha as any legal system likes quantifiable formal rules. Now, there's
one series where the quantifiable rules are based on certain logical assumptions.
It's just we're not going to assess every case on its own
merits. I remember reading many years back an article about a lawyer
that spoke
about a family lawyer and how we've become so litigious that it
used to be the rule was that when there was a divorce,
they would just always give the custody of a child to the
mother unless there was a real real evidence that the mother was
not a fit parent. Then they decided that's not
fair, so they decided okay, to the best parent, and then they
get all of these psychologists to testify or whatever. Whoever winds up
losing custody winds up then
suing and
not suing. Okay, that
maybe it's nicer for some of the fathers that get custody but
in terms of the welfare of the children. So the point is,
you know, sometimes there are formal rules that are based on assumptions
and logic, but we need formal rules in order for the system
to run smoothly. That I think we can understand why we're not
going to assess every case on its own merit. This case of
סוטה Sotah you're absolutely correct. This is more hard to understand because
here it's purely formalistic. There's no logic behind it. It's not a
rule based on some logic. It's purely formalistic. So I don't have,
you know, a good answer for that other than a lot sometimes
within certain like, you know, of these areas of like טומאה Tum'ah
which are already more like obscure, you know, more ritualistic I should
say, not obscure,
this degree of formalism I don't find as troubling. It is more
of a challenge when it's something like כשרות Kashrut or you know
it's something like things which are which are, you know, which you
would want to be much more, you know, rooted in reality.
And it creates stringencies and leniencies.
Right. Sure, it's arbitrary. Right. Once it's arbitrary, it's, you know, it
can go against logical where you'd go logically in either direction. That
is absolutely true, yes.
Are you saying the סוטה Sotah is טמאה? Temei'ah? It's just to
her husband, she's not, she shouldn't touch תרומה. Terumah.
No no right, this טומאה Tum'ah is only in terms of sexual
issues.
So he creates the situation. It's his mental state is the determining
factor here.
Well, and how he acted on his mental state, that he warned
her and then how she reacted to that.
And that he's jealous of a particular person. Right. He decides that
to to
that she's suspicious.
Right. So nothing may have taken place in the real world. Correct.
It's not analogous to the מקוה. Mikvah.
No, it has to have been at least a ספק.
Safek. Right.
So the difference is
a, you know, a substantial.
Right. So the difference is
and I don't want to get caught up in סוטה Sotah because
we have a whole מסכת Masechet devoted to it, but the difference
is and this is important to note, you know, while סוטה Sotah
is very troubling for many reasons, חז"ל Chazal at least and I'm
not saying they did this from a feminist perspective, they did this
from a legalistic perspective, they took what the תורה Torah describes as
which is exactly what you just described עבר עליו רוח קנאה וקינא
את אשתו Avar Alav Ruach Kinah VeKina Et Ishto basically it's just
pure jealousy of a husband and he schleps his wife to the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and they they legalized it. And they actually
said we're talking only in specific concrete circumstances that give us basis
to assume something's happened. So he has to formally warn them, warn
her in front of witnesses, she has to go into seclusion in
front of witnesses. So they made it not just purely his, quote,
you know, something purely internal, and they made it much external and
to give it some concrete basis for doubting, for for being suspicious
about what might have happened. Okay, so so it's not just, you
know, it's not all in his head, there so that's why also
they're able to make these types of comparisons that there's some concrete
reason of wondering what happened. But it you know, but it definitely
has the issues that you raise and that's more to discuss when
we do סוטה. Sotah. Alright, so let's continue now. So the first
point is we had a lovely statement which is let's not focus
on private and public domain, let's look at whether there's a basis
for doubt. But it says no no no, we go by formal
rules, fine. Here we're not going by the סוטה Sotah rules, why?
Because it started with a חזקת טומאה Cheskat Tum'ah and therefore that
remains. That's the rabbis that say it's וודאי טמא. Vada'i Tamei. Now
what about רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says it's a doubt? Well,
he's easier, he's straight סוטה Sotah application, or so it would seem.
רבי שמעון סבר, Rabbi Shimon Savar, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds, כי
סוטה, Ki Sotah, it's just like a סוטה. Sotah. מה סוטה ברשות
הרבים טהורה, Ma Sotah Bireshut HaRabbim Tehorah, the same way a סוטה
Sotah there's a doubt what happened and we say in a public
she's טהורה, Tehorah, הכא נמי, Hacha Nami, here too by this case
about the מקוה, Mikvah, ברשות הרבים טהורה, Bireshut HaRabbim Tehorah, if there's
a doubt because you don't know whether the מקוה Mikvah was full
or not, then if it was in a public domain we assume
it's okay. The גמרא Gemara says okay, but one minute, אי מה
סוטה, I Mi Sotah, if סוטה Sotah is your model, how about
the other half of your statement? אימא כי סוטה, Eima Ki Sotah,
let's make it like סוטה. Sotah. מה סוטה ברשות היחיד טמאה, Ma
Sotah Bireshut HaYachid Temei'ah, the same way a סוטה Sotah we say
also though if it's in a private domain we rule her as
וודאי טמאה Vada'i Temei'ah for her husband unless it's clarified otherwise by
the סוטה Sotah procedure, הכא נמי, Hacha Nami, here too ברשות היחיד
טמאה, Bireshut HaYachid Temei'ah,
why not say in the מקוה Mikvah case it's definitely טמאה? Temei'ah?
Why do you say doubtful? Okay, yes it's clear רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, although the גמרא Gemara said both are learning from סוטה, Sotah,
really it's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon learning from סוטה. Sotah. It's clear
that that's his model, he's distinguishing between private and public domain, but
what's not clear is why in the private domain he doesn't go
the whole distance, why is it ספק Safek and not וודאי. Vada'i.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. הכי השתא, Hachi Hasha,
what type of comparison is that?
התם, Hatam, יש רגלים לדבר. Yesh Raglayim Ladavar. By a סוטה, Sotah,
this is sort of addressing your point רבקה, Rivka, I don't know
if you're happy with the answer, but this is addressing it. By
a סוטה Sotah there's a reason to assume that she's definitely טמאה
Temei'ah until we can know
otherwise, why? שהרי קינא לה ונסתרה, Sheharei Kinah Lah Venisterah, because he
warned her and she went into seclusion. It has support? Is that
what it means? Okay, so... okay, so same thing here, which means
in this... Right. So anyway, it means that there's a good basis
for suspicion. There's a good reason to think something happened why because
he got jealous and then she went into private into hiding now
really the point
is is it the jealousy that's the basis? So you have to
remember that חז"ל Chazal say that the word קינה kina again not
פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim which is just jealousy means a
קינה kina expressed in a warning that he warned her in front
of witnesses I don't want to see you being with that man
going into private with that man. So the fact that he warned
her and then she went ahead and violated that and went private
that's not just she was in seclusion with somebody but clearly the
husband was suspicious clearly she'd been warned she disregarded that so that
gives us at least some basis for being suspicious. So that is
why maybe the תורה Torah will treat her as
טמאה. temei'ah. הכא מאי רגלים לדבר איכא? Hacha mai raglayim ladavar ika?
Here who knows what happened? Now it's חסר. chaser. Who knows when
it became חסר? chaser? Today, yesterday, a week ago, there's no reason
to suspect it happened earlier or no good reason to say it
happened yesterday more than today and therefore it remains a ספק safek
as opposed to the סוטה Sotah case where it seems like we
have we're inclined to think that it actually did happen. So now
רש"י Rashi says based on this that according to this and this
is actually a surprise because we always know this principle of רשות
היחיד טמא reshut hayachid tamei based on סוטה Sotah that actually רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon would reject that. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say
what we learn from סוטה Sotah is רשות הרבים טהור reshut harabim
tahor but רשות היחיד reshut hayachid is ספק. safek. The only reason
סוטה Sotah is it's only סוטה Sotah that's treated as ודאי טמא
vadai tamei because there is particular reason to think that it happened.
Okay but in normal cases in a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid it
would remain ספק safek and he disagrees with that general principle.
But what about the fact that it started out טמא? tamei?
Ah that he was...
that's not a factor for him because you actually did an act
that could have changed the status so at the end of the
day it all boils down to what was the status of that
act.
But we also know that the מקוה mikvah steadily evaporated.
I understand but for him at the end of the day it
all boils down to what was the status of that act so
he's not impressed by the חזקת טומאה. chezkas tumah. Okay so that's
one answer which really changes the whole model of סוטה. Sotah. So
it's true he learned it from סוטה Sotah but he has a
different model than we would have expected.
ואיבעית אימא Ve'iba'is eima if you want you could say היינו טעמא
דרבי שמעון hainu ta'ama deRabbi Shimon here's his reason גמר סוף טומאה
מתחילת טומאה. gamar sof tumah mitechilas tumah. So it's not only the
reason of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we're still really saying he learns
from סוטה Sotah but we're emphasizing that this
is
maybe also touches on what Michael said. This is the end of
the process not the beginning. The סוטה Sotah is the question of
did she become טמאה temei'ah again this is using the word טמא
tamei in a different way did she commit adultery. The normal way
in which we apply the model of סוטה Sotah is somebody touched
something they don't know did they touch the מת mes did they
not touch the מת. mes. Well where did it occur in רשות
הרבים reshut harabim or רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid? So that's all תחילת
טומאה. techilas tumah. Did טומאה tumah come into being in the first
place? That's where you use the model of סוטה. Sotah. Can you
apply it to this case which is Michael's point where it started
טמא tamei and it was put into the מקוה mikvah and the
question is did the טומאה tumah go away? Can you use the
model of סוטה Sotah to dictate how to decide that case? So
that's the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the
חכמים. Chachamim. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says he גמר סוף טומאה מתחילת טומאה gamar sof
tumah mitechilas tumah he says you can learn the end of the
process from the beginning of the process. מה תחילת טומאה Mah techilas
tumah the same way the initial becoming טמא tamei ספק נגע ספק
לא נגע safek naga ספק לא נגע safek lo naga there's a
doubt if this person touched the corpse or not we apply the
סוטה Sotah rule and we say ברשות הרבים טהור bireshut harabim tahor
that in רשות הרבים reshut harabim you are טהור tahor אף סוף
טומאה af sof tumah even the end of the process by dunking
in the מקוה mikvah ספק טבל ספק לא טבל safek taval safek
lo taval was it a good טבילה tevilah or not even though
you started and we knew you were definitely טמא tamei at the
end of the day there's a question was it a good טבילה
tevilah or not a good טבילה tevilah ברשות הרבים טהור bireshut harabim
tahor and we will use the סוטה Sotah model yes we're not
impressed with the fact that you started off טמא tamei at the
end of the day it all boils down to was it a
good טבילה tevilah or not and we'll use the סוטה Sotah model
to say טהור. tahor. Okay. ורבנן Verabbanan and the rabbis will say
הכי השתא? hachi hashta? What type of comparison is that? התם גברא
בחזקת טהרה קאי Hasam gavra bechezkas taharah ka'i there the person starts
as being טהור tahor and did he touch the corpse or not
so we can say if it's public domain טהור tahor
מספקא לא מחתינן ליה לטומאה mispika lo machtinan leh letumah out of
doubt you're not going to declare him to be טמא. tamei. There
we can be lenient and say if it's in a public domain
you're טהור. tahor. הכא גברא בחזקת טומאה קאי Hacha gavra bechezkas tumah
ka'i here you started off being טמא tamei and your question is
was it a good טבילה tevilah or not מספקא לא מפיקינן ליה
מטומאתו mispika lo mafkinan leh mitumaso so we're not going to go
against your status quo. In both cases we're inclined to favor your
status quo. So when your status quo is טהור tahor and you
touched it unless it's in a private domain where we have a
special rule from סוטה Sotah but if it's not that we will
say you remain טהור tahor we retain your status. status quo and
by the מקווה mikvah we're going to ignore סוטה Sotah because again
we're going to be inclined to go by status quo and we're
going to say if the status quo is טמא tamei you retain
that unless you definitely did a good טבילה. tvila. So at the
end what this גמרא Gemara did before it used the phrase תרתי
לריעותא tartei lerei'usa which was much more generic two bad things here
it's much more specific and it goes back to what we said
yesterday about what makes the מקווה mikvah case different. Your status quo
started as טמא tamei and therefore the חכמים Chachamim are going to
say if there's any doubt you remain טמא. tamei. Don't talk to
me about סוטה Sotah it's not similar here your status quo started
as טמא tamei by סוטה Sotah and all those places you started
טהור tahor and therefore here you're definitely טמא tamei whereas רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon so really what the חכמים Chachamim are saying is לא
למדו מסוטה lo lamdu miSotah it's not about סוטה Sotah it's the
status quo of טמא tamei whereas רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no
I still want to apply סוטה Sotah rules and I'm going to
say רשות הרבים טהור rishus harabim tahor רשות היחיד rishus hayachid maybe
I'll say ספק safek because he says we don't really say from
סוטה Sotah definitely טמא tamei we really say ספק safek so really
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is insisting apply the rules and the חכמים
Chachamim are saying it's not similar.
Yes I just want to make sure I understood because we do
say that סוטה Sotah ברשות היחיד birshus hayachid is טמאה tameiah but
not according to
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon it's ספק safek other than the one case
of סוטה Sotah but the general rule
no no that's what I'm saying so in סוטה Sotah I said
that you know they
then yes because of רגלים לדבר raglayim ladavar right but
then so basically that means if you apply it to any other
case since only there רגלים לדבר raglayim ladavar and any other case
is sort of like half since you don't really have
רגלים לדבר raglayim ladavar we don't have any rule to learn from
סוטה Sotah so the rule is the general rule is ספק safek
if it's a ספק safek it's a ספק. safek. It's okay I
mean
if you don't believe me the first narrow line of רש"י Rashi
ושמע מינה דקסבר רבי שמעון בשאר ספק טומאה דעלמא נמי ברשות היחיד
תולין u'shma mina d'kasavar Rabbi Shimon bishar safek tumah d'alma nami birshus
hayachid tolin so
what
does that mean להלכה l'halacha though it's
תולין tolin ספק safek so you don't burn it you don't eat
it no but
למעשה l'maiseh then what do you do
dunk the כלים kelim again yeah dunk it again
so basically it means essentially טמא tamei
no because if you already used it on something then the תרומה
Terumah then that has a טומאת ספק tumas safek added onto itself.
When did she become טמאה tameiah
I'm sorry what seclusion she's אסורה asura to her husband from the
moment she secludes not
after from the moment in which there's the ספק safek there's the
basis of doubt of what happened which is the moment of seclusion
not the moment that he warned her even if she had secluded
with the man you know for a year prior to warning her
that does not create the סוטה Sotah status until he warns her
and then she secludes again.
That's just automatic don't need בית דין Beis Din to
no but you need witnesses to see her seclusion.
Okay so that is that whole comparison now we are almost done
I know this is all very abstract but we have one more
comparison to another non-נידה Niddah case and then we will turn back
to as I said the subjective and biological realities of the נידה
Niddah so let's take a look and also sort of larger policy
concerns so let's have one first final comparison ומאי שנא ממבוי u'mai
shna miMavoi how is it different than the מבוי Mavoi דתנן de-tnan
השרץ שנמצא במבוי ha-sheretz shenimtzah b'Mavoi you found a dead rodent in
a courtyard which was something that would cause טומאה tumah one of
the שרצים sheratzim that causes טומאה tumah and you're concerned that you
walked over it and touched it and you know and so on
and then you handled תרומה Terumah whatever the case might be so
מטמא למפרע metamei l'mafrei'a we have to assume that anybody who's been
in the courtyard became A that it was in the courtyard and
B presumably that people definitely touched it right that's really two questions
I'm not sure why we're assuming people touched it but here we're
going to focus on the issue that we're assuming it was in
the courtyard and
therefore anybody who's passed through it is טמא tamei מטמא למפרע metamei
l'mafrei'a it causes טומאה tumah retroactively עד שיאמר בדקתי את המבוי הזה
ולא היה בו שרץ ad sheyomar badakti es haMavoi hazeh v'lo hayah
bo sheretz until you can say well you've got a big crowd
until you can say that I checked it you know I actually
on Sunday went through the whole courtyard looking for rodents and I
saw there were no rodents which is obviously analogous in the מקווה
mikvah case in the נידה Niddah case we say she's טמאה tameiah
retroactively according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai until the last time she
checked right so there's obviously some comparisons here או עד שעת הכיבוד
o ad sha'as ha-kibud
or until the last time it's been swept so they had regular
cleaning right Mondays and Wednesdays nine to eleven opposite side of the
street parking
and the assumption is that when they're sweeping they primarily do it
for cleanliness but they also know about טומאה tumah concerns so they're
also checking it out and making sure there's no problem so even
though nobody tells you oh I checked it you don't have to
go back further than the last time it was swept because you
know whoever swept it was also checking okay so here you have
it's very analogous again why we're assuming somebody walked over the שרץ
sheretz or touched the שרץ sheretz I don't know but anyway the
problem is now and we are retroactively assuming or concerned that it
was in the past until you know for certain otherwise sounds like
a straight בית הלל Beis Hillel approach so let's take a look
would בית שמאי Beis Shammai disagree with that or is there a
point of
distinction?
Now could שמאי Shammai disagree?
But שמאי, Shammai, not even בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
Anyway, התם נמי, hasam nami, so
let's see what the
גמרא, Gemara, but it's interesting, the
גמרא Gemara gives the גמרא Gemara an opportunity to make distinctions. So
let's see what the
answer is. התם נמי כיון דאיכא שרצים דגופיה ושרצים דאתו מעלמא כתרי
לריעותא דמי. hasam nami kivan de’ika sheratzim degufei vesheratzim de’asú me’alma k’tarei
lere’usa dami.
Now here's where the idea of two bad things clearly is very
abstract because although the גמרא Gemara is saying "two bad", we've been
emphasizing what it really means is something started with like by the
מקוה mikveh case, a status quo as being טמא. tamei. Here the
גמרא Gemara just makes it two bad things, whatever generic. And what
are the two bad things here? Well, rodents can come from anywhere.
They can come from rodents that, you know, live in the מבוי,
mabuy, burrow under the מבוי mabuy and come up, or it could
be a rodent that's come from, you know, from the next town
over. So since there are multiple sources of rodents and multiple ways
things could get here, there's a lot of reasons to think that
this thing, you know, not to assume it happened just now, to
be concerned it happened earlier. Okay, so that's a very generic "two
bad things", not at all as formalistically as we had before about
the status quo of טומאה. tum’ah.
Just two ways the מקוה mikveh is being
emptied...
That's right, but the comparison isn't to the מקוה, mikveh, it's the
same הלכה halacha as the מקוה, mikveh, that here it is טמא
tamei retroactively. We have to distinguish it from the נדה niddah case.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ואיבעית אימא, ve’iba’is eima, if you
want you could say, because that wasn't such a satisfying answer, היינו
טעמא דשמאי, hainu ta’ama deShammai, here's the reason, הואיל ואשה מרגשת בעצמה.
ho’il ve’ishah margeshes be’atzmah.
And here we finally, to distinguish it from the שרץ sheretz case,
finally introduce a new issue, and the rest of the דף daf
will be focused much more on this, not these sort of formalistic
issues about previous חזקה, chazakah, חזקה chazakah now, did you start off
טמא, tamei, start off טהור, tahor, but the reality, the
biological-psychological reality of the נדה. niddah. And here the first thing it
is saying is, you know why שמאי Shammai says she's טהורה? tahorah?
I mean, if you think about it, we brought all these cases,
מקוה, mikveh, חבית, chavis, מבוי, mabuy, they all say we're concerned retroactively,
right? So you could make a lot of distinctions, which the גמרא
Gemara had a fun time doing. But maybe rather than saying... making
all those distinctions about those cases are different, תרי לריעותא tarei lere’usa
etc., maybe it's just the נדה niddah that's the special case. Why
is the נדה niddah the special case? So that's interesting. So we're
going to give a couple of reasons now for why נדה niddah
could be a special case according to שמאי Shammai and say it's
only טמאה teme’ah now. The first reason is, as Joe said, a
woman knows when she's getting her period, אשה מרגשת בעצמה. ishah margeshes
be’atzmah. And what's particularly fascinating about this is when we talk about
הרגשה, hargashah, and this is a... something that comes up a few
important places in the גמרא נדה, Gemara Niddah, it... it makes the...
it turns the woman from being an object back into being a
subject, meaning it turns from her basically being treated as this מקוה
mikveh with running water and when did this happen to, wait a
minute, she's actually having her own inner experience of this, her own
subjective experience about this, and that is, you know, relevant here. So
it really subjectifies the woman as opposed to objectifies her, and that's
what שמאי Shammai says. Since a woman knows when she's getting her
period, we don't have to assume maybe it happened yesterday, two days
ago, three days ago. Okay, you know, if it happened, I would
have felt it, I would have known. And since I didn't know
and I didn't experience it, then we could assume it only happened
now. Now, of course, תוספות Tosfos asks you a question, but wait
a minute, but right now, you know, let's say you didn't have
a הרגשה, hargashah, that's the reason you're presumably asking the question. Now
maybe you could say he only said it when you have a
הרגשה, hargashah, it doesn't sound like that. Okay, so תוספות, Tosfos, fine,
it might be true that it sometimes happens, but as a rule,
we're not going to be concerned about the past because as a
rule, I, you know, the woman will say, "I will know when
I'm getting my period." So we are not going to be concerned
that it happened in the past because that's not consistent with my
subjective reality. Okay, so that is the very important now answer making
נדה niddah a special case. We're going to have a couple of
ways in which we're going to say נדה niddah could be special.
Yes?
You said she knows when she's getting her period. There are actually
two cases. One is when she has a... when she has her
period regularly on the same day of the month, and the other
is right now she's feeling she's having a period.
Right, so having it on the same day of the month is
even הלל Hillel agrees to that, that's אשה שיש לה וסת. ishah
sheyesh lah veses. That was in the משנה. mishnah. That's not what
שמאי Shammai is saying. שמאי Shammai is saying she could not be
regular, but she still knows when she's getting her period. Okay. And
therefore, we're not going to be concerned that it happened... we're going
to say it happened without her being aware. Okay. So let's take
a look.
אישתנאי, ishtanai, that's because generally, because it could be specific unless she
engages in something very strenuous which she might not have felt...
Right. ...but as a rule, and therefore as a rule, we're not
going to be concerned. Okay.
הואיל ואשה מרגשת בעצמה. ho’il ve’ishah margeshes be’atzmah. והלל, veHillel, what's הלל
Hillel say back to that? קסבר מרגשת מי רגלים היא. kesavur margeshes
mei raglayim hi. No, women might... he's not denying that they have
a sensation, but they might be discounting it. Maybe she did... maybe
she did bleed yesterday, but why didn't she realize she was bleeding?
Because maybe she was urinating at the time and she thought that
that feeling she was having was the feeling of urinating and not
a feeling of getting the period. I'd be interested to hear from
the women's perspective here. They have no idea what that הרגשה Hargasha
is.
Right. Ask women, what is that experience like?
Don't call in a group of women and ask. Why?
Some later rabbis do speak to women because הרגשה Hargasha becomes an
important halachic principle and you'll have some פוסקים Poskim who speak to,
you know, they say that we talk to women to try to
understand what is this הרגשה Hargasha and so on. So in modern,
yes. But once or twice you had the בית יוסף Beis Yosef
talking, saying, I spoke to a lot to women, but not about
the הרגשה Hargasha issue,
but within הלכות נידה. Hilchos Niddah. So that's what הלל Hillel says,
you know, maybe she did have the הרגשה Hargasha and she discounted
it. ולשמאי, U'l'Shammai, okay, but obviously that doesn't need a response. שמאי
Shammai isn't concerned about that. Women know when they're getting their period.
ולשמאי, U'l'Shammai, says the גמרא, Gemara, האיכא ישנה, Ha'ika Yeshena, one minute,
but a woman might be asleep when she got her period and
then she wouldn't have experienced it so you can't say she definitely
would have known. So the גמרא Gemara says, ישנה נמי אגב צערא
מיתערא, Yeshena nami agav tzara mit'ara, you know what, even if she's
asleep, because of the little sort of discomfort, pain that it'll cause,
she'll wake up. She'll be aware that it's happening. מידי דהוה אהרגשת
מי רגלים, Midi de'hava a'hargashtas mei raglayim, the same way you wake,
you know when you have to go to the bathroom when you're
sleeping, right? You know when you have to urinate, you feel that
and you wake up. So the גמרא Gemara again making the comparison
now for שמאי Shammai to the feeling of urination, which is, you
know, yes, a sensation men could feel in that part of the,
that analogous part of the body and you could have some sensation
that it's happening.
So therefore says, yes, so according to שמאי Shammai we're not concerned.
We think even if she's sleeping, she'll know when she's got her
period.
For בית הלל, Beis Hillel, it sounded like it was a sensation...
actually בית הלל, Beis Hillel, not בית הלל, Beis Hillel, of course,
הלל. Hillel.
Rare that we have actual הלל Hillel and שמאי.
Shammai. So הלל Hillel sounds like it's a sensation of an actual
flow by מי רגלים Mei Raglayim where שמאי Shammai is using the
sensation for an urge.
Well, not necessarily, because
הלל Hillel could also be the urge and the pressure... שמאי Shammai
rather, right? הלל, Hillel, I'm sorry, הלל, Hillel, right? It just says
הרגשת מי רגלים. Hargashtas mei raglayim. Which part of the הרגשה? Hargasha?
הרגשה Hargasha that you need to go to the bathroom? The הרגשה
Hargasha that you're actually urinating? I mean I said urinating, so that
but it's not clear in the גמרא. Gemara. But yes, it is
a question here about what, how much did חזל Chazal understand that
they were making this comparison.
According to שמאי, Shammai, it seems it's the הרגשה Hargasha not about
the actual flow of urination.
Right, according to שמאי, Shammai, the only comparison to מי רגלים Mei
Raglayim is not in the nature of the sensation but as an
analogy. The same way you wake up when you have to go
to the bathroom, a woman will wake up when she feels she's
menstruating. But what is that feeling? You don't have any evidence according
to שמאי Shammai what he thinks that feeling is. But you're right,
הלל Hillel who says it could be confused with מי רגלים Mei
Raglayim feels that there's some aspect of, you know, of the sensation
of urination or feeling you have to urinate that could be compared
to it.
And but this whole שאלה Shayla is, why don't we ask this
question on רב שמעון Rav Shimon too, because in other words, isn't
this... isn't this מבוי שפתוח, Mavoy she'patuach, right?
Okay, I don't want to get into that. Maybe we could, but
we're not focusing on that. So let's move on. We're on to
the next part. Alright, so let's take a look now as the
גמרא Gemara continues. האיכא שוטה, Ha'ika Shota, how about a woman according
to שמאי Shammai that is a שוטה? Shota? A woman that is,
you know, not of right mind, not rational, or acts... I mean
there's whole constant of exactly how you define שוטה. Shota. Sometimes we
simply say insane, but it's not exactly insane. Somebody that sort of,
you know, is not really fully aware of their surroundings and is
not thinking clearly and so on. So without... that was not a
precise definition. But anyway, so the גמרא Gemara actually talks about, you
know, how a שוטה Shota knows that she's טמאה Temeiah or not
and how she becomes טהורה, Tehorah, her friends have to help her
and have to help her check, and the whole... like this comes
up, we'll be seeing cases in the משנה Mishna about this. But
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but if that woman is not really
conscious and cognitive of what's really going on, so how can you
say that she would have known when she had her period?
Let's see the answer. So the גמרא's Gemara's answer is, מודה שמאי
בשוטה. Modeh Shammai b'shota. Okay, so in that case he'll grant, fine,
that case he'll agree to, but every other case he'll say women
will know. Just let's just finish this point and then get to
your question.
וכל הנשים קתני, V'chol hanashim katani, 'all women', it says, so presumably
that includes שוטה? Shota? כל הנשים פקחות. Kol hanashim pikchot. No, it
means all women that are of sort of right mind. It doesn't
literally mean all women. אי הכי נשים, Ei hachi nashim, so then
just say 'women'. Why do you say כל? Kol? לאפוקי מדרבי אליעזר.
L'afukei mi'd'Rabbi Eliezer.
No, because כל Kol is coming to tell you it's a much
bigger group than other people usually have. It's certainly bigger than רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דאמר רבי אליעזר ארבע נשים. D'amar Rabbi Eliezer arba
nashim. Because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says four women are דין שעתן,
Dayan Sha'atan, they don't have to be concerned retroactively, they're only concerned
from the moment they see. So he's willing to grant four groups
of women. שמאי Shammai is saying it's not limited, all women, not
literally all, there's the שוטה Shota case, but all normal circumstances. It's
not limited to special cases. קא משמע לן כל הנשים, Ka mashma
lan kol hanashim,
all women. So therefore yes, we will exclude the one case. it's
still important to say כל הנשים kol hanashim to mean all women
under normal, under all, under normal circumstances. Yes, רבקה? Rivka?
Can a שוטה shoteh be halakhically married?
So no, if she she can't, she cannot do an act of
קידושין, kiddushin, a שוטה, shoteh, because she is not considered בר דעת.
bar da'at. But if she was not a שוטה shoteh when she
was married, then the marriage remains binding even if she becomes a
שוטה. shoteh. The same is true for the man.
But why שוטה shoteh then? If it's a mental deficiency then...
Well first of all you have to realize that this has relevance
not just for sex, this has relevance for טומאה. tumah. Not necessarily
is what I'm saying. It could be because it could be a
married woman. No not necessarily is what I'm saying. It could be
because it could be טומאה tumah whatever. But it could be a
woman that was halakhically married and then and then she like let's
say somebody has really has like a psychotic episode right so when
they're married they're of
bright mind so there's a whole I mean that's discussed a lot
in חגיגה Chagigah and there's a whole question about how to apply
it nowadays so I'm leaving it purposefully a bit vague but certainly
the point is to speak about somebody that is not operating with
clear mental faculties and not really fully cognizant of their surroundings. You
know there's a real challenging issue I should say and you're probably
aware about this is in cases of divorce. If the woman is
a שוטה shoteh giving her גט get is that possible she's not
cognizant and the חרם רבינו גרשום Cherem Rabbeinu Gershom and if the
man is a שוטה shoteh then how can you write a גט.
get. So those are really really challenging issues. Okay so now we're
saying that according to שמאי Shammai again נדה niddah is a special
case she's aware. Now we have one final question. ואיכא כתמים. Ve-ika
kesamim. So how about כתמים? kesamim? כתמים kesamim are stains found on
clothes and you don't exactly know where the stains come from. If
there's no basis for saying the stains came from elsewhere then the
woman has to assume that they came from her. Now again this
was a pretty unhygienic society they didn't have tight fitting underwear so
you have a red stain on your clothes did it come from
when I was שחטינג shechting the chicken in the backyard? Did it
come from where did it come from? But if you can't attribute
it to other sources she has to assume it came from her
and she's טמאה temeah at least דרבנן. de-rabbanan. Okay that's the הלכה
halakha of stains. Now the question about stains is
a stain clearly the reality is is that she doesn't know she's
had her period. The basic case of a stain is you turned
around and you saw there was a stain on the clothes. So
therefore clearly that case as opposed to it could happen she could
have her period without a sensation here the whole category of stains
is you just discovered something that happened without any awareness. So according
to שמאי Shammai he should admit that those cases are טמא tamei
retroactively because those cases the whole category occurs without a sensation. So
maybe
למימרא דתנן כתמים דלא כשמאי? Lemeimra de-tenan kesamim de-lo ke-Shammai? I'm sorry
no no. The גמרא Gemara is saying the opposite. למימרא דתנן כתמים
דלא כשמאי. Lemeimra de-tenan kesamim de-lo ke-Shammai.
Let's say the opposite. Since שמאי Shammai assumes that a woman will
always have a sensation that accompanies bleeding or almost always then according
to שמאי Shammai we should say that כתמים kesamim are never from
the woman, right? If he's really saying she's always aware so I
don't have to be concerned retroactively, okay. So if I don't know
where this stain came from I should assume not from me because
if I was having my period I would have been I would
have had the sensation. So maybe שמאי Shammai rejects the entire category
of כתמים. kesamim. Very interesting issue.
Well the question is whether נדה niddah blood has to be menstrual
blood or not? Oh
I see what you're saying. Meaning maybe it's blood that makes you
טמאה temeah but it wasn't actually her period. That is a good
question because definitely you can have bleeding not during the period and
it could still create טומאה tumah and right שמאי Shammai is not
considering that possibility. So that is an excellent point that Jay makes
which is true that the הרגשה hargashah normally we're assuming accompanies the
menstruation. What about other bleeding that could make her טמאה temeah that
is not actual menstruation? So the גמרא Gemara is discounting that which
is fascinating because it's assuming that that's really the primary thing we
have to be concerned about is the menstruation but it's an excellent
point. So the גמרא Gemara says למימרא דתנן כתמים דלא כשמאי. Lemeimra
de-tenan kesamim de-lo ke-Shammai. Maybe שמאי Shammai rejects the category of כתמים.
kesamim. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye says, מודי שמאי בכתמים.
Modeh Shammai be-kesamim. No, he would agree to the category of כתמים.
kesamim. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? בציפור לא נתעסקה, Be-tzippor lo nit'aska, she
wasn't שחטינג shechting a chicken and that's essentially what it means. ובשוק
של טבחים לא עברה, U-ve-shuk shel tabbachim lo avra, she didn't go
to the butcher meaning the whole reason we say she's טמאה temeah
by כתמים kesamim is when there's no other source of the blood.
So האי דמא היכא אתא? Hai dama heikha ata? Where else could
this blood have come from? So is it true that he says
it's impossible to bleed without a sensation? Maybe this is also Jay's
point, maybe it's not even menstrual blood. It's impossible he does say
that you'll usually know but he's not going to reject כתמים kesamim
when there's no basis, no way you could say it came from
elsewhere, then you have to admit that it did come from the
woman. Okay so that's one reason why נדה niddah is special because
and that's very important because it very much focuses on the subjective
experience. Reason number two that נדה niddah is special, אי בעית אימא...
Iba'it eima... here's the reason נדה Niddah special not הרגשה hargasha היינו
טעמא דשמאי hainu ta'ama d'Shammai here's Shammai's reasoning דאם איתא דהוה דם
מעיקרא הוה אתי d'im isa d'hava dam meikara hava atei
not so much her experiential reality but the biological reality blood will
come right out of the body remember I said that the woman
becomes טמאה tmeia as soon as it goes past through the cervix
into the vaginal canal
but the question is how much are we concerned that it delays
there before coming out of the body so Shammai will say I'm
not concerned I assume it comes out immediately it doesn't get stuck
there and since it doesn't get stuck as soon as she sees
that's when it happened now so basically what Shammai is saying is
why are you concerned it happened yesterday where was it yesterday
so Hillel presumably is concerned where was it it was still in
her body it had passed through the cervix and not yet come
out of the body so Shammai says I'm not concerned about that
I assume it'll come out as soon as she's bleeding and therefore
you know why I am not concerned it happened yesterday because you
only saw today you only saw today it only happened today now
of course you could imagine scenarios let's say she's sitting on a
chair you know she's lying on a bed and she wakes up
in the morning right so it could have come out right away
but it could have come out last night rather than this morning
so it doesn't really cover all the scenarios but the basic point
that Shammai is saying is you are concerned that she didn't see
it because it didn't come right out from her body I'm not
concerned about that I assume when she's bleeding it'll come right out
and when she sees it that's when it happened so the גמרא
Gemara דאם איתא דהוה דם מעיקרא הוה אתי d'im isa d'hava dam
meikara hava atei it's okay so that is his reasoning דאם איתא
דהוה דם מעיקרא הוה אתי d'im isa d'hava dam meikara hava atei
it would have come out before והלל v'Hillel and Hillel will say
כותלי בית הרחם העמידוהו kotlei beis harechem he'emiduhu
the walls of the now בית הרחם beis harechem normally means of
the uterus held it back but of course it can't really mean
the walls of the uterus held it back because then she's not
yet a נדה Niddah okay so it really has to mean here
the vaginal walls you know held it back it got caught up
after it passed through the cervix and no I am concerned who
knows when she actually bled she saw today but again this is
a whole thing which makes נדה Niddah you know the entire נדה
Niddah you know so much of נדה Niddah hinges on the הלכה
halacha that she's טמאה tmeia when it's in her body all the
ideas of בדיקות bedikos and here all the ideas that we have
doubts when she became טמאה tmeia because it all happened internally when
it can't be at least observed to the outside eye maybe experienced
from the woman but not observed so Hillel says that's why I'm
concerned well
all we know that I mean I don't know but we know
that I know you know when women do בדיקות bedikos sometimes they
find bloodstains so clearly there could be blood in there that's not
yet come out I mean not a lot but there could be
I assume when she's really well when the period starts I mean
Sally I'm sure could correct me but you know it often starts
slowly and then picks up so maybe at the very beginning when
it's just a few then maybe it could actually delay no Sally
anything you want to add okay
so let's take a look בשמאי b'Shammai what does Shammai say כותלי
בית הרחם לא מוקמי דמא kotlei beis harechem lo mukmi dama I'm
sorry that doesn't happen the walls of the either the vaginal canal
or the walls of the uterus they don't keep the blood from
coming out okay so now the גמרא Gemara says משמשת במוך מאי
איכא למימר meshameshes b'moch mai ika l'meimar what about a woman who
actually is using birth control a specific type which is the מוך
moch which is like a sponge essentially I mean the most similar
thing for us would be a diaphragm so you know and there
were some women that are allowed or obligated to use a מוך
moch because they were concerned about them being pregnant and it would
lead to a סכנה sakana so if they have this מוך moch
in their body for us the reality could just as well be
let's talk about a tampon
so then Shammai should be concerned because there's a reason the blood
didn't come out there was the מוך moch so now of course
the question is where did you find the blood then you should
have found it on the מוך moch not on something else but
maybe who knows maybe you didn't check the מוך moch you threw
it out and then the rest of the blood came out but
at least in that case you should be concerned because it won't
come out right away אמר אביי amar Abaye so said Abaye מודה
שמאי במשמשת במוך modeh Shammai b'meshameshes b'moch fine that case he'll agree
that case you will be טמא tamei retroactively you know you'll have
to be concerned about the past רבא אמר Rava amar Rava said
מוך נמי אגב זיעה מיכווץ moch nami agav zeia michvatz the מוך
moch which we wonder therefore how effective it was Rava said you
know what the מוך moch because of the sweat inside of the
body I don't know if there's sweat glands inside the body but
whatever because of the liquids inside of the body it'll shrivel a
little bit so blood if she's been bleeding it would have come
out even with the מוך moch the מוך moch is not completely
and
he's not מודה modeh it doesn't completely
stop up of course then you wonder like I said how effective
it is but okay ומודה רבא u'modeh Rava but even Rava would
agree מוך דחוס moch dachus
if it was a tight מוך moch then he would say yes
then at least that case Shammai would agree to so now we
have two reasons Shammai says נדה Niddah special one because she experiences
it the other because the blood comes out right away one a
psychological reality the other a biological reality and that makes מוך moch
the נדה Niddah case special and not the other cases that are
the ones that are different so now the גמרא Gemara says ומאי
איכא בין הני לישני להא לישנא *Umai ika bein hani lishni l'ha
lishna*, what difference does it make between the other answers we gave
where we made formalistic differences about תרתי לריעותא *tartei l'reuta* and חזקת
טומאה *chezkas tumah* and this approach where we're giving much more, you
know, real world distinctions? So איכא בינייהו *ika beinaihu*... the difference is
whether we should ask all the questions we asked before... which is,
I know, but it's like a practical point, okay? It's whether all
those other examples are relevant and have the need to make those
distinctions that we made. להאי לישנא איכא למימרמינהו *L'hai lishna ika l'mirminhu*
from the approach we had of assuming it wasn't a special physical
reality with the
נדה niddah *Niddah*, they were all just then they were all comparable.
There was nothing special about נדה niddah *Niddah*. So we can say
well how's it similar to חבית *chavis* and different and make distinctions
תרתי לריעותא *tartei l'reuta*, all that type of stuff, so we can
make the comparisons. להני לישני *L'hani lishni* according to this approach that
נדה niddah *Niddah* is distinct, לית למימרמיהו *leit l'mirmiahu*, you cannot make
those types of, you know, there's no basis for comparison. The whole
approach of שמאי Shammai *Shamai* is נדה niddah *Niddah* is a special
case. Okay, which clearly, yes, the whole approach of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is changing radically. Now we're talking about the what's
the unique aspects of נדה *Niddah* and not these more abstract types
of comparisons. Okay, also a נפקא מינה *nafka mina* would be like
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said about, you know, whether מופתחת *mufteches* would
matter, whether שוטה *shota* would matter. According to the first approach, it
was not about the actual reality of the case and those special
cases would be not relevant. So which is, which is more or
less what the גמרא's *Gemara's* going to move on to. ומאי איכא
בין האי לישנא להאי לישנא *U'mai ika bein hai lishna l'hai lishna*,
what difference does it make if your approach is the question about
הרגשה *hargasha* or your approach is the issue about the blood coming
out right away? לאביי איכא מוח, לרבא איכא מוח דחוק *L'Abaye ika
moch, l'Rava ika moch dachuk*. Whether the difference is a woman using
a מוח *moch* according to אביי *Abaye* or מוח דחוק *moch dachuk*
according to רבא *Rava*. If it's about the idea that the blood
comes out right away, then that would be a case that שמאי
Shammai, *Shamai* would agree. שמאי Shammai. *Shamai* would say you do have
to be concerned. If it's about the experience הרגשה *hargasha*, the sensation,
then שמאי Shammai *Shamai* would not agree. You could also have said
the נפקא מינה *nafka mina* was שוטה *shota*, right? If it's about
the sensation, then שמאי Shammai *Shamai* would say that case I have
to agree, cause the woman isn't aware. And if it's about the
blood coming out right away, he wouldn't agree. So all of the
qualifications we gave before about שוטה *shota* and מוח *moch*, those would
be the differences based on which approach. So basically just to restate
it, if it's not about the special reality of נדה *Niddah*, general
rules, חזקה *chazakah*, טומאה *tumah*, retroactive and so on, then no special
cases matter cause נדה *Niddah* is just a generic case. Okay, if
it's about the unique characteristics of נדה *Niddah*, then it depends which
unique characteristics. If it's about her experience and her הרגשה *hargasha*, then
the question about שוטה *shota* matters, that case. If it's about the
biological reality and the blood coming right out, then the physical reality
about מוח *moch* and using some type of a, you know, tampon
or diaphragm, that would make a difference. Okay, so that's how each
approach, you know, says whether these things make a difference or not
and which things make a difference. Yes.
Would they possibly apply the first approach to the issue of טומאה
וטהרה tuma v'tahara. *tumah v'taharah* that a woman who is a possible
נדה *Niddah* would be, whereas the second approach to the actual issue
of whether she can have
relations?
Oh, that is a good question and we're going to get to
that... you know, because your point is that the first approach maybe...
you know,
let's hold off that. But yes, your point is that maybe we
should make distinctions about how much we're going to be concerned for
טומאה וטהרה *tumah v'taharah* versus בעילה *beilah* on the first one maybe
because it's somewhat more formalistic maybe טומאה וטהרה *tumah v'taharah*,
it's definitely possible. Okay, I'm not going to say more about that
right now. Let's take a look at the גמרא *Gemara* as it
continues.
Okay. Now תניא כהאי לישנא דאי איתא דדם הוה מעיקרא הוה אתי
*Tanya k'hai lishna d'ee isah d'dam hava mei-ikra hava ati*. We actually
have a ברייתא braita *braita* that supports the approach that the issue
is about the blood coming out right away. אמר לו הלל Hillel.
לשמאי *Amar lo Hillel l'Shamai*, Hillel said to Shamai, אי אתה מודה
בקופה שנשתמש בה טהרות teharos בזוית זו ונמצא שרץ sheretz בזוית אחרת
שהטהרות הראשונות טמאות *Ee ata modeh b'kuppa shenishtamesh bah taharos b'zavis zo
v'nimtza sheretz b'zavis acheres shehataharos harishonos temei-os*? Wouldn't you agree, let's say
here you had your box filled with תרומה terumah. *terumah*, and you
were over here taking some תרומה terumah *terumah* grain out and sifting
it or who knows what you were doing, and then you emptied
the box and you found a שרץ sheretz *sheretz* on the other
side of the box. So when did that שרץ sheretz *sheretz* get
here? Right, you know, you emptied the box and now we're after
you were dealing with your טהרות teharos *taharos*. Was that שרץ sheretz
*sheretz* there when you were dealing with your טהרות *taharos*? So הלל
Hillel, *Hillel* says to שמאי Shammai *Shamai*, wouldn't you admit that in
that case you have to be concerned the שרץ sheretz *sheretz* was
there when you were dealing with it? How is the נדה *Niddah*
any different? Right? She's bleeding now, we should be concerned that it
happened before. So אמר לו אבל *Amar lo aval*, he said yes,
I do admit to that case, אבל הן אמרו משנה וקיבלו מנין
*aval hen amru mishnah v'kiblu minyan* yes, I can see that point,
but ומה הפרש בין זו לזו *u'mah hefresh bein zo l'zo*, but
what's the difference between the two? לזו יש לה שוליים, לזו אין
לה שוליים lezu yesh la shulayim lezu ein la shulayim. *L'zu yesh
lah shulayim, l'zu ein lah shulayim*. A box has a floor, the
woman where the blood coming out of doesn't have a floor. So
right the blood is flowing out, there's no floor to catch, which
means that in this case what he's saying is which is being
reframed as: when a woman is bleeding, there's nothing to stop the
blood from coming out, so if she had bled earlier, you would
have seen it, the blood comes right out, which is the idea,
that's Shammai's idea, the explanation of Shammai, that the blood will come
right out. Whereas in this case of the box, you know what,
it's not that way when the, it's not that now that you
saw this שרץ means that this was the first time the שרץ
got here. The box had a floor, the שרץ could have been
sitting in the box for for for a day, you know, for
a for a week. So that's why the שרץ is different. There
the שרץ could have been there, but in the נדה case, the
blood would have already come out and there's no concern.
And the שרץ is dead or alive?
Dead. Has to be dead. It has to be dead. Okay. רב
אמר, Rav amar, so that's a ברייתא braita. that supports that approach.
רב אמר, Rav amar, now with that's a third answer why
נדה special, טעמא דשמאי, ta'ama de'Shammai, this you have to tell David,
משום ביטול פריה ורביה. mishum bitul pirya ve'rivya. A policy concern. Not
just a biological or psychological issue, but a policy concern. You know
what, being concerned retroactively, maybe there's a basis, maybe not. Obviously if
it was biblical you would not be able to say this, so
maybe rabbinically there's a we would be concerned in the past. But
I'm going to have to override that and not be concerned. Why?
Because if women are always being concerned that when they bleed now,
maybe they had bled a day ago, then
then people aren't going to have sex, because they're now you know
because they're always going to be afraid, well maybe maybe actually bleeding
now and I just you know we just don't know about it.
So therefore you do not want to be saying you have to
be concerned retroactively because people will it'll lead to not having kids,
it'll lead to not having sex. Okay because it'll be very clear
that we're concerned that the woman might be bleeding internally without it
actually having come out yet. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we
taught a similar ברייתא. braita אמר לו שמאי להלל, amar lo Shammai
le'Hillel, שמאי Shammai. said to הלל. Hillel אם כן בטלת בנות ישראל
מפריה ורביה. im ken bitalta benot Yisrael mi'pirya ve'rivya. Look, I get
your your approach. You want to do like we would do by
the קופות kupot and the מקוה mikvah and all those cases. You
want to be concerned retroactively like we normally would be. But how
about the policy implications? People are going to stop having sex. Okay
so that's quite fascinating that that is sort of the over, and
it's also fascinating that it's שמאי, Shammai because we would have assumed
something like this from הלל, Hillel you know the whole idea that
הלל Hillel was the sensitive one, not שמאי. Shammai There are a
couple of stories like there's also the case about the עבד, eved,
the חצי chatzi free עבד, eved, that שמאי is very concerned about
the עבד's eved ability to marry and so on, maybe they're both
linked by a concern about having kids, you know פריה ורביה pirya
ve'rivya is the way it's framed. It's just quite interesting. Okay. So
now the גמרא says, ומאן דתני האי לישנא הא תני כי האי
לישנא,
u'man de'tani hai lishna
ha tani ki hai lishna, דאם איתא דהוי דמי קרא הוי אתי.
d'im ita d'havi dami kara havi atei. So if you say the
reason is פרו ורבו, pru u'revu, what about the other ברייתא braita
that was the whole thing about the box that made it clear
that the concern was that the blood would have already come out?
הלל הוא דקא טעי. Hillel hu de'ka ta'ei. No, הלל Hillel misunderstood.
הוא סבר, hu savar, הלל Hillel thought, טעמא דשמאי דאם איתא דהוי
דמי קרא הוי אתי. ta'ama de'Shammai d'im ita d'havi dami kara havi
atei. He thought שמאי's issue had to do with the biological reality,
that the blood would definitely come out.
וקמקיש לה לקופה, ve'kama'atkish lah le'kuppa, and he's actually questioned on the
box of תרומה. terumah אמר ליה שמאי, amar lei Shammai, and שמאי
said back, טעמא דידי, ta'ama didi, you know if you want to
know my real reason, it's really a policy reason, משום ביטול פריה
ורביה. mishum bitul pirya ve'rivya. ולמאי דקא טעית, u'lemai de'ka ta'eita, you
were making a mistake and you think that I was more about
the physical reality, דקמקישת לה לקופה, de'kama'atkisht lah le'kuppa, you were comparing
it to the קופה, kuppa, I could still give you an answer
even about how the physical reality by נדה is less of an
issue. לזו יש לה שוליים לזו אין לה שוליים. This has a
floor, this doesn't. So therefore by the נדה there's not only do
I have a policy position but I even have a basis for
supporting it like in more normal halakhic argument that you would have
the blood already would have come out.
So because of the biology I can make this policy?
Or because of the policy I'm going to underscore, right. So it's
true, but the גמרא sort of
doesn't isn't assuming that, it's one or the other, but yes, you
definitely could say that they inform one another. And now it's going
to ask the reverse. So that's how you would explain it if
the real reason was the policy. But now what if the real
reason is the the biological sort of read? ולמאן דתני האי לישנא,
u'leiman de'tani hai lishna, the one that says the other way, the
other approach, that it's about the biological reality, הא תני כי האי
לישנא, ha tani ki hai lishna, what do you do with the
ברייתא that says it's about the policy concern, משום ביטול
פריה ורביה? mishum bitul pirya ve'rivya? הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's what
it says, הכי קאמר ליה הלל לשמאי. hachi ka'amar lei Hillel le'Shammai.
So here's what הלל Hillel said to שמאי. אין טעמא קאמרת, in
ta'ama ka'amart, you know what, the idea that the blood would have
come out already and she would have known right away, that's טאקע
taka a good answer. Okay, you said well, דאם איתא דהוי דמי
קרא הוי
אתי. d'im ita d'havi dami kara havi atei. If there was blood
it would have come out, that's a good answer. מיהו, mi'hu, even
though I concede that really she should not be טמא tamei retroactively,
עשה סייג לדבריך, asay seyag le'devarekha, at least make a safeguard. You
know that's what the Rabbis are always doing. They're making safeguards and
buffer zones. Again, something we normally assume is more שמאי's, you know,
role than הלל's. So הלל's saying, look, in terms of, you know,
sort of strict application of the law, you're right, she should be
טהור. tahor. who are retroactively. But I'm saying make a rabbinic safeguard.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, and he said back, no, אם כן ביטלת
בנות ישראל מפריה ורביה. im kein bitalta bnot Yisrael mipriya urviya. No,
I'm not interested in making safeguards. I have other concerns here that
it will lead to people not having kids, not having sex. והלל,
VeHillel, מפריה ורביה
מי קאמינא? mipriya urviya mi kamina? לטהרות דקאמינא. letoharos dekamina. Hillel says
look, I didn't say that you can't have sex the last 24
hours of... how do you stop having sex the last 24 retroactively?
There was once an article in New York Times about a terrible
signage in New York and there was a letter to the editor
afterwards that said the best or worst example of this he once
had was that he was like on I don't know what it
is New Jersey Turnpike and you know he's passing whatever exit 11
and signs said you know exit closed use exit five miles back.
So alright so anyway so Hillel is saying look we're not talking
about אסור-ing assur sex, we're talking about one minute טומאה וטהרה. So
in the last time period between
checks, anyway you don't know till after the fact anyway. So he's
saying the only question is what do we say about the תרומה
you touched. Nobody is saying anything about the fact about what happened
about the fact that you had sex you know within the last
24 hours. So ושמאי, veShammai, Shammai would say לטהרות נמי לא. letoharos
nami lo. You can't split it from the way that it the
impression it creates on people.
דאם כן לבו נוקפו ופורש. de-im kein libo nofo paresh. Once you
start worrying for טהרות and you say that you have to now
worry the last you know x amount of hours, 24 hours however
since the last time you checked, you're telling the person that we're
concerned you know the man and the woman we're concerned that she
the woman is bleeding and you just don't know about it. So
once that's an ongoing concern in their practice even if it's for
טהרות and imagine you say okay all the תרומה that you handled
we can't eat anymore. The fact that we had sex last night
you're not going to you know somehow you're going to manage to
compartmentalize that? No, you're going to associate one with the other. It
says something about the assumptions that's being made about the woman's status.
So this is a bad policy move. So according to this שמאי
is a little different I want to point out the nuance between
the two answers. The first answer seems to say that the real
strict law should have said she should have been טמאה מספק t'mei'ah
misafek but policy is overriding that strict it can't obviously be biblical
but overriding that strict application of the law for the sake of
this concern of פריה ורביה. priya urviya. The second version is lighter.
The second version is no the strict law actually is she's טהורה.
tehorah. Hillel wanted to make though a new safeguard and Shammai says
no new safeguards we're not going to make because of this policy.
So the first version of it was much stronger that the policy
was even overriding what the strict law would have been. One last
question and then we'll end for today.
What about the questions that came up separately if there is ספק
טהורה safek tehorah or even something rabbinic if there's ספק טמא safek
tamei or rabbinic טמא tamei does that make a difference for what
you can do with it?
Right clearly yeah and it's all it's all rabbinic everybody's clearly agreed.